{
  "reference_number": "10713",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "The government should set a target now. I believe that the situation is urgent. At Svalbard (between Norway and the North Pole) the\n sea surface temperatures on July 6 over the last 5 years have been; 2014 -0.8degrees C, 2015 6.2 deg C, 2016 8.3 deg C, 2017 14.4\n\n deg C, 2018 16.6 deg C. More at https://arctic-news.blogspot.com/2018/07/disappearance-of-arctic-sea-ice.html The subsequent\n melting of the ice will trigger various feed back loops that will lead to even more ice melting which leads to less sunlight being\n reflected back into space, which leads to global warming which leads to wilder weather and sea level rises. ,"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "An example of the changing climate is that now in summer boats can pass around the north of Russia."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I prefer the $ to be spent in NZ where we have better control over the validity of emission reductions."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Extreme weather events may require us to reduce emissions more rapidly. The emissions budgets should not be changed as long\n term certainty is important. However major changes in scientific understanding would be an exception."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The aim of the bill is to have something \"above\" politics. Any exceptions would need to clearly be spelt out in the legislation"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I agree that the Government and the Climate Commission should take the following factors into consideration when advising on and\n\nsetting budgets: • scientific knowledge regarding climate change • technology relevant to climate change • economic\ncircumstances and the likely impact of a decision on the economy, as well as the competitiveness of particular sectors of the\n\neconomy • fiscal circumstances and the likely impact of the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing • social\ncircumstances and the likely impact of a decision on fuel poverty • energy policy and the likely impact of a decision on energy\n\nsupplies and the carbon and energy intensity of the economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes we must specify a strict time frame for producing a plan."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Need to work with climate change and emissions experts from universities and scientists. The most important thing is that emissions\n\nreduce. The Government’s policy plans to meet emission budgets should be comprehensive, fair, cost-effective, environmentally\nsustainable, and reflect a commitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes - the Commission should not be a decision-making body. However, the Government should be legally required to consider and\nformally respond to the Commission’s advice, and to provide an explanation if they do not act on it."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with the following collective expertise: • climate change policy (including emissions trading and emissions taxes • resource\neconomics and impacts (including social impacts, labour markets and distribution) • climate and environmental science including\n\nmātauranga Māori • experience with addressing adaptation challenges like planning, insurance and local government • risk\nmanagement • engineering and/or infrastructure • community engagement and communications. • business competitiveness •\n\nknowledge of the public and private innovation and technology development system. I think expertise in public health is also\nimportant."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We have a responsibility to our pacific neighbors some of whom clearly will find their islands uninhabitable."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I agree with the proposed functions below, but recognize that nuance is required in terms of how local councils are involved: • a\nnational climate change risk assessment • a national adaptation plan • regular review of progress towards implementing the national\nadaptation plan • an adaptation reporting power"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The public wants to know."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "My favourite camping ground at Kuotuna is not far above sea level. I hope that this work i successful so that my children can use it in\nthe future."
    }
  ]
}
